John Edward Foster Papers
John Edward Foster Papers
1860-1865
Foster, John Edward.
0.5 linear ft.
Union soldier (1834?-1864), served with Vermont Volunteers. Collection includes correspondence with family in Vermont during Civil War service; some letters from brother, Julian, to family members; miscellaneous material including two diary pages, a list of debts, and a pencil drawing of encampment of Company E, 2nd Regiment, Vermont Volunteers.
148986
Biographical History
John Edward Foster (1834-1864) was a native of Tunbridge, Vermont. He enlisted in the Union Army in 1860 with Company E of the 2d Regiment, Vermont Volunteers. He served as a foot soldier and wagoneer until his death in 1864 at the Battle of the Wilderness. Julian Foster, his younger brother, enlisted in January of 1864 and died in December of that same year, of causes unspecified in these papers.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Edward Foster Papers consists of correspondence and miscellaneous.
The majority of the Correspondence is to his family in Vermont, and covers topics such as bad food, poor winter quarters, and the horrors of battle. Occasional letters are more light-hearted, such as one which describes a snowball attack on another regiment and an expedition to steal chickens. In two letters (12 Nov 1862 and 22 Apr 1864) he refers to the soldiers' intense loyalty to "Little Mack" (General George McClellan).
The collection includes a few letters from John's brother Julian to his family, written in the months between his enlistment and his death. There are also some letters from John and Julian's parents and siblings, as well as a few letters of condolence from relatives and friends. Many of the letterheads and envelopes carry Union symbols, drawings and slogans.
Miscellaneous material contains a pencil drawing of the encampment of Company E, a note to the paymaster from John Foster, and two small fragmentary pages of a diary.
Arrangement of the Collection
Letters are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
has a number of collections of Civil War letters and correspondence. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Civil War (U.S.); Foster, John Edward Correspondence.; Foster, Julian.; Soldiers -- United States.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives.; United States -- History, Military -- To 1900 -- Sources.; Correspondence.; Soldiers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1860 (Box 1)
  - 1861, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - 1862, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - 1863, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - 1864, 13 folders (Box 1)
  - 1865 (Box 1)
  - Envelopes, 1861-1865 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellany, 1861-1862 (Box 1)